A Guide to the Historical Commission of Falls Church Records, 1955-2012
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
The Historical Commission of Falls Church Records, 1955-2012
Falls Church History Room, Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Records Group 1-3
14 boxes
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Historical Commission, upon a Resolution of the City Council, established the Mary Riley Styles Public Library, specifically its Falls Church History Room (or Virginia Room as it was called then) to hold, process, and make accessible the materials of the Commission.
Administrative History
The Historical Commission of Falls Church "provides information and advice on historical matters for the city government, develops criteria for the identification of historic buildings and sites, and makes recommendations on recognizing and preserving such structures and sites. The Commission identifies, collects, preserves, and displays the evidence and records of the city's history, and recommends measures for preserving city publications, displays and other materials of historic interest. It also proposes programs and projects involving city history. The Historical Commission advises the City Council, the City Manager, the Planning Commission, the Architectural Advisory Board, and other officials and bodies." Website: http://www.fallschurchva.gov/266/Historical-Commission
The Falls Church Historical Development Commission, formed in 1955, was the forerunner of the Historical Commission. The Historical Commission was designated an official commission of the City of Falls Church in 1965. The Falls Church Public Library, later the Mary Riley Styles Public Library, was designated the official repository of the Historical Commission papers.
Of special interest are the projects listed in Series 7 and the Archaeological Assessment in Series 9. There is a separate Record Group (1-9) containing records of the Historical Commission Historical Heritage Symposia, although some of those records are within these files in Series 10.
Scope and Content
The Historical Commission, upon a Resolution of the City Council, established the Mary Riley Styles Public Library, specifically its Falls Church History Room (or Virginia Room as it was called then) to hold, process, and make accessible the materials of the Commission. The series was organized as follows:
Series 1: Incorporation/Organization
Series 2: Annual Reports
Series 3: Membership
Series 4: Meetings (Note: includes meeting announcements, agendas and minutes)
Series 5: Budget and Finance
Series 6: Correspondence
Series 7: Projects
Series 8: Archaeological Assessment
Series 9: Individual Reports on Houses in the Archaeological Assessment
Series 10: Symposiums
Series 11: Subject files
Series 12: Land Records
Series 13: Falls Church Public Library/Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Arrangement
Many files were housed in the Falls Church History Room of the Mary Riley Styles Public Library. Other files were donated by Maurice Ternan. These were organized by the archivist using the headings used by the Historical Commission and incorporated into the existing files as shown in the Scope and Content.
Contents List
*File contains photograph(s) **File contains a floppy disc ***File contains a DVD ****File contains slides
- Series 1: Incorporation/Organization (Box 1)
  - Falls Church Historical Development Commission, 1955-1956 (Folder 1)
  - Charter and Resolutions, 1965-1976 (Folder 2)
  - Collection/Acquisition Policy, 1974 (Folder 3)
  - Collection Inventory (has index cards), 1978 (Folder 4)
  - Collection Register, 1978 (Folder 5)
  - Contracts, 1974-1977 (Folder 6)
  - Copyrights, 1971-1972 (Folder 7)
  - Gifts and Acquisitions, 1964-1966, 1976-1979 (Folder 8)
  - Goals and Objectives, 1968-1980 (Folder 9)
  - Resolutions and Agreements of the Historical Commission, City Council and the Library, 1965-1989 (Folder 10)
  - Virginia Room Log Book, 1980-1989 (Folder 11)
- Series 2: Annual Reports (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1960-61, 1966, 1967, 1969 (Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1970-1979 (Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1982-1985, 1989 (Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1993, 1997 (Folder 4)
- Series 3: Membership
  - AASLH Membership, 1976-1985 (Folder 1)
  - Early Membership, 1965-1982 (Folder 2)
  - Members, 1965-1980, 1993 (Folder 3)
  - Members, Honorary, 1966, 1972 (Folder 4)
  - Membership lists, 1965, 1976-1993 (Folder 5)
- Series 4: Meetings (Box 1)
  - Meetings, 1965 (Folder 1)
  - Meetings, 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Meetings, 1967 (Folder 3)
  - Meetings, 1968 (Folder 4)
  - Meetings, 1969 (Folder 5)
  - Meetings, 1970 (Folder 6)
  - Meetings, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - Meetings, 1972 (Folder 8)
  - Meetings, 1973 (Folder 9)
  - Meetings, 1974 (Folder 10)
- Series 4: Meetings (continued) (Box 2)
  - Meetings, 1975 (Folder 11)
  - Meetings, 1976 (Folder 12)
  - Meetings, 1977 (Folder 13)
  - Meetings, 1978 (Folder 14)
  - Meetings, 1979 (Folder 15)
  - Meetings, 1980 (Folder 16)
  - Meetings, 1981 (Folder 17)
  - Meetings, 1982 (Folder 18)
  - Meetings, 1983 (Folder 19)
  - Meetings, 1984 (Folder 20)
  - Meetings, 1985 (Folder 21)
  - Meetings, January-June 1986 (Folder 22)
  - Meetings, July-December 1986 (Folder 23)
  - Meetings, January-June 1987 (Folder 24)
  - Meetings, July-December 1987 (Folder 25)
  - Meetings
  - Meetings
  - Meetings
- Series 4: Meetings (continued) (Box 3)
  - Meetings, 1988 (Folder 26)
  - Meetings, 1989 (Folder 27)
  - Meetings, 1990 (Folder 28)
  - Meetings, 1991 (Folder 29)
  - Meetings, 1992 (Folder 30)
  - Meetings, January-June 1993 (Folder 31)
  - Meetings, July-December 1993 (Folder 32)
  - Meetings, January-June 1994 (Folder 33)
  - Meetings, July-December 1994 (Folder 34)
  - Meetings, January-June 1995 (Folder 35)
  - Meetings, July-December 1995 (Folder 36)
  - Meetings, 1996 (Folder 37)
  - Meetings, 1997 (Folder 38)
  - Meetings, 1998 (Folder 39)
- Series 4: Meetings (continued) (Box 4)
  - Meetings, 1999 (Folder 40)
  - Meetings, 2000 (Folder 41)
  - Meetings, 2001 (Folder 42)
  - Meetings, 2002 (Folder 43)
  - Meetings, 2003 (Folder 44)
  - Meetings, 2004 (Folder 45)
  - Meetings, 2005 (Folder 46)
  - Meetings, 2006 (Folder 47)
  - Meetings, January-June 2007 (Folder 48)
  - Meetings, July-December 2007 (Folder 49)
  - Meetings, 2008 (Folder 50)
  - Meetings, January-June 2009 (Folder 51)
  - Meetings, July-December 2009 (Folder 52)
  - Meetings, 2010 (Folder 53)
  - Meetings, 2011 (Folder 54)
  - Meetings, 2012 (Folder 55)
- Series 4: Meetings (continued) (Box 5)
  - Meeting Agendas, 1996 (Folder 56)
  - Meeting Agendas, 1997-2002 (Folder 57)
  - Procedures, 1965-1989 (Folder 58)
- Series 5: Budget and Finance (Box 5)
  - Budget and Finance, 1963-1970 (Folder 1)
  - Budget and Finance, 1970-1971 (Folder 2)
  - Budget and Finance, 1971-1972 (Folder 3)
  - Budget and Finance, 1972-1973 (Folder 4)
  - Budget and Finance, 1973-1974 (Folder 5)
  - Budget and Finance, 1974-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Budget and Finance, 1975-1976 (Folder 7)
  - Budget and Finance, 1976-1977 (Folder 8)
  - Budget and Finance, 1977-1978 (Folder 9)
  - Expenses and Capital Outlay Replacement Detail, [n.d.] (Folder 10)
  - Supplies, 1983-1986 (Folder 11)
- Series 6: Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Folder 9)
- Series 6: Correspondence (continued) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Folder 10)
  - Correspondence – Planning Commission, 1971-1977 (Folder 11)
- Series 7: Projects (Box 6)
  - Archaeology, 1972-1975, 1986 (Folder 1)
  - Architectural and Historical Research Program on Pre-Civil War Houses in Falls Church, Proposal, 1970-1974 (Folder 2)
  - Architectural Inventory, 1967-1975 (Folder 3)
  - Barn Museum Feasibility Study,* 1969 (Folder 4)
  - By Fence and Fireside, 1964, 1968, 1977 (Folder 5)
  - Cherry Hill, 1965-1969 (Folder 6)
  - Cherry Hill, 1970 (Folder 7)
  - Cherry Hill, 1971 (Folder 8)
  - Cherry Hill, 1972-1973 (Folder 9)
  - Cherry Hill, February 1975 (Folder 10)
  - Cherry Hill, March 1975 (Folder 11)
  - Cherry Hill, April-December 1975 (Folder 12)
  - Cherry Hill, 1976-1977 (Folder 13)
  - Cherry Hill, Archaeology, 1970-1972 (Folder 14)
  - Cherry Hill Barn, 1971 (Folder 15)
  - Cherry Hill Barn, 1975-1976 (Folder 16)
  - Cherry Hill Dedication, 1976 (Folder 17)
  - Cherry Hill, Deed, 1955-1956, 1967-1968 (Folder 18)
  - Cherry Hill, Dickey, Correspondence, 1972 (Folder 19)
  - Cherry Hill, Dickey, Correspondence, 1973 (Folder 20)
  - Cherry Hill, Dickey, Correspondence, 1974 (Folder 21)
  - Cherry Hill, Dickey, Report, April 1973 (Folder 22)
  - Cherry Hill, Dickey, Report, June 1973 (Folder 23)
- Series 7: Projects (continued) (Box 7)
  - Cherry Hill, Dickey, Specifications, 1974 (Folder 24)
  - Cherry Hill, Fauber, 1966-1968 (Folder 25)
  - Cherry Hill, Furnishings, 1974-1976 (Folder 26)
  - Cherry Hill, Landscaping, 1975 (Folder 27)
  - Cherry Hill, Michael & Michael, Architects, 1975 (Folder 28)
  - Cherry Hill, Planning Commission, 1972-1975 (Folder 29)
  - Cherry Hill, Uses and Functions, 1971-1981 (Folder 30)
  - Cherry Hill, Uses and Functions, 1983-1986 (Folder 31)
  - Descriptive Material – Belle Grove Plantation near Middletown, Virginia (Folder 32)
  - Descriptive Material – Carroll County Farm Museum, Westminster, Maryland (Folder 33)
  - Descriptive Material – Dennis Historical Centers, South Dennis, Massachusetts (Folder 34)
  - Descriptive Material – Farmers’ Museum, Cooperstown, New York (Folder 35)
  - Descriptive Material – National Capital Parks, DC, 1969 (Folder 36)
  - Descriptive Material – National Colonial Farm, Bryan Point, Prince Georges County, Maryland (Folder 37)
  - Descriptive Material – Pennsylvania Farm Museum, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania (Folder 38)
  - Descriptive Material – Old Sturbridge Village, Sturbridge, Massachusetts (Folder 39)
  - Descriptive Material – Sloane-Stanley Museum and Kent Furnace, Kent, Connecticut (Folder 40)
  - General, 1970-1984, 1997 (Folder 41)
- Series 8: Archaeological Assessment (Box 7)
  - Application for 1994-1995 State Survey and Planning Funds (Folder 1)
  - Archaeological Assessment, 1994-1998 (Folder 2)
  - Archaeological Assessment, 1999 (Folder 3)
- Series 8: Archaeological Assessment (continued) (Box 8)
  - Archaeological Assessment, 2000 (Folder 4)
  - Archaeological Assessment, 1994 (Folder 5)
  - Archaeological Assessment, January-April 1995 (Folder 6)
  - Archaeological Assessment,** September 1995-September 1996 (Folder 7)
  - Architectural Inventory, May 1, 1975 (Folder 8)
  - Architectural Survey and Assessment in the City of Falls Church, October 18, 1994 (Folder 9)
  - Architectural Survey and Assessment in the City of Falls Church, Community Meeting, February 7, 1995 (Folder 10)
  - Architectural Survey and Assessment in the City of Falls Church, Draft Final Report Outline, June 30, 1995 (Folder 11)
  - Architectural Survey and Assessment of the City of Falls Church, Draft Final Report, August 31, 1995 (Folder 12)
  - Architectural Survey and Assessment of the City of Falls Church, Draft Final Report, August 31, 1995, with comments, November 6, 1995 (Folder 13)
  - Architectural Survey and Assessment of the City of Falls Church, Draft Final Report, February 8, 1996 (Folder 14)
  - Assessment of Archaeological Resources in the City of Falls Church, Virginia, Draft Report, September 27, 1999 (Folder 15)
- Series 8: Archaeological Assessment (continued) (Box 9)
  - Assessment of Archaeological Resources in the City of Falls Church, Virginia, Technical and Cost Proposal, August 31, 1998 (Folder 16)
  - Chronologic Historic Register of Certified Structures, October 1990 and May 1993 (Folder 17)
  - City of Falls Church Design Guidelines, Final Draft, July 2001 (Folder 18)
  - Demolition of Certifiable Structures on 1969 Architectural Inventory (Folder 19)
  - Extant Archaeological Site Forms and Reports, City of Falls Church, Virginia, [n.d.] (Folder 20)
  - Inventory of Outbuildings on Official Register Sites, July 1992 (Folder 21)
- Series 9: Individual Reports on Houses in the Archaeological Assessment (Box 9)
  - Annandale Rd – E -- 303 (Folder 1)
  - Broad St – E – 209, 225 (Folder 2)
  - Broad St – E – 302, 312, 402, 513, 708 (Folder 3)
  - Broad St – W – 509, 706, 715, 920 (Folder 4)
  - Cherry St – N – 218, 223, 301, 412 (Folder 5)
  - Columbia St – E – 214, 219, 407 (Folder 6)
  - Fairfax St – E – 115 (Folder 7)
  - Great Falls St – 300, 532, 539, 543 (Folder 8)
  - Grove St – 311 (Folder 9)
  - Jefferson St – E – 115, 215, 422 (Folder 10)
  - Lawton St – 203 (Folder 11)
  - Lincoln Ave – 313, 508 (Folder 12)
  - Maple Ave – N – 310 (Folder 13)
  - Maple Ave – S – 307 (Folder 14)
  - Midvale St – 209 (Folder 15)
  - Oak St – N – 303, 305, 502 (Folder 16)
  - Oak St – S – 203, 206 (Folder 17)
  - Park Ave – 312, 816, 905 (Folder 18)
  - Parker Ave – 905 (Folder 19)
  - Patterson St – 208 (Folder 20)
  - Walden Ct – 502 (Folder 21)
  - Washington St – N – 220, 258, 282, 333, 400 block (Folder 22)
  - Washington St – S – 121 (Folder 23)
  - West St – N – 201, 301 (Folder 24)
- Series 10: Symposiums (Box 9)
  - First Historical Symposium, 1994 (Folder 1)
  - Second Historical Symposium, 1995 (Folder 2)
  - Fourth Historical Symposium, 1997 (Folder 3)
  - Fifth Historical Symposium, 1998 (Folder 4)
- Series 11: Subject Files (Box 10)
  - 400th Anniversary of Jamestown, Virginia,*** 2005-2007 (Folder 1)
  - Archives Committee, 1986 (Folder 2)
  - Big Chimneys,** 1999 (Folder 3)
  - Big Chimneys,* 2002-2003 (Folder 4)
  - Black History (Folder 5)
  - Blacksmith Shop and Historic Triangle (Folder 6)
  - Burke House, 6718 Montour Drive, Fairfax* (Folder 7)
  - Certified Local Government (Folder 8)
  - Cherry Hill, 1995-1999 (Folder 9)
  - Cherry Hill Farm, Falls Church, Virginia (Tony P. Wrenn, January 1971) (Folder 10)
  - Cherry Hill Farm, Falls Church, Virginia (Tony P. Wrenn and Henry H. Douglas, July 1977) (Folder 11)
  - Church History Committee of Greater Falls Church, Church Histories* (Folder 12)
  - Church History Committee of Greater Falls Church, Minutes and Agendas, 1995-1997 (Folder 13)
  - Citizens for Responsible Falls Church Development, 1996 (Folder 14)
  - City Center Development (Folder 15)
  - City of Falls Church Street Map, [n.d.] (Folder 16)
- Series 11: Subject Files (continued) (Box 11)
  - Civil War, Living History Demonstrations,* 1995-1997 (Folder 17)
  - Civil War, Living History Demonstrations,* 1998-2003 (Folder 18)
  - Civil War Trails in Northern Virginia, May 1996-February 1977 (Folder 19)
  - Civil War Trails in Northern Virginia, March 1977-December 1998, 2000 (Folder 20)
  - Civil War Trails in Northern Virginia Photographs* (Folder 22)
  - Council Minutes, 1973-1974 (Folder 23)
  - The Courier of Historical Events, Northern Virginia Association of Historians, April 1981 and January 1984 (Folder 24)
  - Crossman, Mrs. A. F., Plat showing Property, [1910?] (Folder 25)
  - Crossroads Area, Proposed Development Plan, March 1974 (Folder 26)
  - Cultural Resources Committee, 1999-2001 (Folder 26)
  - The Dulin Site: Excavation Report I: 1977-1978, July 1979 (Folder 27)
  - Falls Church and Segregation in the 20th Century, M.J. Terman, June 2000 (Folder 28)
  - Falls Church Organization List, January 1984 (Folder 29)
  - Falls Church Parking and Circulation Plan, Maps 5-8, January 1965 (Folder 30)
  - Falls Church Public Schools: Report on Instruction, 1962-1963 (Folder 31)
  - Frady Park, October 2004 (Folder 32)
  - Henderson, Edwin B. (Folder 33)
  - Henderson, Edwin B. II (Folder 34)
  - Henderson, James H. M. (Folder 35)
  - Henderson, Mary Ellen Meriwether**** (Folder 36)
  - Henderson House* (Folder 37)
- Series 11: Subject Files (continued) (Box 12)
  - Historic House Tours, 1986-2003 (Folder 38)
  - Historic Preservation and Economic Development, 1995-1999 (Folder 39)
  - Historic Structures (Certified List), 1990-1996 (Folder 40)
  - Historic Trail Marker Program, 1993, 2006 (Folder 41)
  - History in Education, 2000-2002 (Folder 42)
  - History of Falls Church – “Stepping Stones” – short version, 1994-1995 (Folder 43)
  - Interjurisdictional Park Task Force, 1995-2000 [Northern Virginia Boundary Stones] (Folder 44)
  - The Iron Worker, Fall Issue, 1950 (Folder 45)
  - Lawton House,* April 1965 (Folder 46)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Folder 47)
  - Oakwood Cemetery (Folder 48)
  - Podolnick, Dr. Nelson, Dedication, 2001 (Folder 49)
  - Preservation Partners Task Force, 2006-2007 (Folder 50)
  - Proctor House, 1995 (Folder 51)
  - Proctor House {blueprints], 1996 (Folder 52)
  - Publications (Folder 53)
  - Roll of White Voters Registered in the Town of Falls Church, [948] (Folder 54)
  - Roll of Women Voters, 1920-1921 (Folder 55)
- Series 11: Subject Files (continued) (Box 13)
  - Rolling Roads, 1994 (Folder 56)
  - Scout House (Folder 57)
  - A Statistical Survey of Falls Church: Part I, A Comparison of the 1960 and 1970 Census, October 1975 (Folder 58)
  - Task Force on Cultural Resources, 1999-2000 (Folder 59)
  - Task Force on Cultural Resources, 2001 (Folder 60)
  - Task Force on Cultural Resources, 2002-2003 (Folder 61)
  - Tinner’s Hill, 1996-2006 (Folder 62)
  - Tricentennial Committee, An Historical Guide and Map, 1993-1999 (Folder 63)
  - Tricentennial Committee Planning, (1998-1999) (Folder 64)
  - Tricentennial Eve, 1998 (Folder 65)
  - Veterans Honor Roll for the Falls Church Area, 1998 (Folder 66)
  - Visitor Center/Museum Applications, 1994-1998 (Folder 67)
  - Visitor Center/Museum Proposals, 1994-2002 (Folder 68)
  - We the People, August 1972 (Folder 69)
  - Whittier School Site, 1992-1997 (Folder 70)
  - Wills, Inventories,[excerpts], 1833-1840 (Folder 71)
- Series 12: Land Records (Box 14)
  - Falls Church Land Ownership (Folder 1)
  - Land-Use History (Folder 2)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Falls Church Grants (Folder 3)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Gunnell, Henry, 1773/Land of Nathan Thompson & heirs, 1845-1870 (Folder 4)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Gunnell, William, 1729 (Folder 5)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Harrison, George, 1742 (Folder 6)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Hurle, John, 1728 (Folder 7)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Kidwell, Z[edekiah], 1837 and F.C. Triangle (1846-1879?) (Folder 8)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Pearson, Simon, 1724 (Folder 9)
  - Northern Neck Grants Regan, [Michael], 1729 (Folder 10)
  - Northern Neck Grants, South Falls Church (Folder 11)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Southeast Falls Church, William Gunnell and Thomas Harrison (Folder 12)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Trammell, John, 1729 (Folder 13)
  - Northern Neck Grants, Wren, James, 1773/1778 (Folder 14)
  - Profile, Before 1860 (Folder 15)
  - Profile, 1870 (Folder 16)
  - Profile, 1880 (Folder 17)
  - Profile, 1900 (Folder 18)
  - Profile, 1910 (Folder 19)
  - Profile, 1920 (Folder 20)
  - Profile, 1930 (Folder 21)
  - Profile, 1940-1950 (Folder 22)
  - Profile, After 1950 (Folder 23)
- Series 13: Falls Church Public Library/Mary Riley Styles Public Library (Box 14)
  - Agreements and Resolutions between the Board of Library Trustees and the Historical Commission, 1979 (Folder 1)
  - Agreements and Resolutions between the Board of Library Trustees and the Historical Commission, 1980 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1961, 1965-1978 (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1987, 1990 (Folder 4)
  - Reports, 1983-1985 (Folder 5)